A Guide to the Additional Papers of Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1874-1953
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 June 28-July 15, 20 items. (Box-folder 12:3)
    Ada wrote that she was miserable and lost without Tom. She also wrote about William Powell, Frank Joliffe, Warren Rice and Mame Shriner. Ada also met with J. Madison Spurr to persuade him to return to the band, but he had to remain home to take care of his wife. Tom hired a sixteen year old cornet player named Nelson Kratz to replace Mr. Spurr. Ada wanted to know if he was good looking!
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 July 16-31, 21 items. (Box-folder 12:4)
    Tom wrote that he missed Ada so much he might break the steels on her corset if she were with him. Ada wrote that she wished he could find her a governess position so she could make some money.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 August 1-August 10, 12 items. (Box-folder 12:5)
    Ada wrote that her eyes hurt and that he was the "dearest, truest, best and noblest man on earth."
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 August 13-August 31, 21 items. (Box-folder 12:6)
    Ada mentioned working at [her father's] store and that in years to come their letters would stand as a diary and tell about old times. She also professed her love to Tom.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 September, 10 items. (Box-folder 13:1)
    Ada wrote from her trip to New York and about William Powell. Tom went to Alum Springs, Buena Vista and Winchester. Ada mentioned that Mr. Charles Broadway Rouss was coming for a visit with her father. She ordered Tom to make up a "yarn" to get out of playing in J. Madison Spurr's band because she didn't think it good enough for him.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 October-December, 12 items. (Box-folder 13:2)
    Tom was in a parade with the F. Fire Company and [Union boys] and Ada and her mother felt that he looked too "pure" for the Company. Ada spent Christmas in Baltimore shopping and visited her friends. Tom wrote that he thought that his prospects in Staunton were very good.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1899 n. d., 2 items and a small unidentified photograph. (Box-folder 13:3)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 January 1-15, 19 items. (Box-folder 13:4)
    Tom wrote that the band had a meeting and an election of officers and appointed Tom as the Assistant Director of the Stonewall Brigade Band and Mr. Joseph M. Brereton as Director. He met with the Principal of the Mary Baldwin Seminary. Tom wrote that he would be directing the band when Brereton was away.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 January 16-31, 22 items. (Box-folder 13:5)
    Ada discusses why they could not get married yet. Tom wrote that the people in Staunton were much better educated in music than in Winchester. Tom planned to meet with the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind He praised Brereton as being better than Mr. Spurr. Boer War mentioned.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 February 1-14, 20 items. (Box-folder 13:6)
    There are news clippings about The Commonwealth Club of Richmond presenting The Stonewall Brigade Band with a banner and an announcement that Professor Beardsworth would assist in the music for the Ladies Auxillary at the Y.M.C. A. Tom described his busy schedule. He also sent her a program for one of their performances. He told her that he thought that his chances at the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind were good. He met with three music teachers at the Mary Baldwin Seminary, Professors Aymn, Eisenburg and Ide. Ada wrote more about the Boer War. She also wrote about her father's bad moods burdening her mother.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 February 16-28, 18 items. (Box-folder 13:7)
    Ada wrote to wish Tom luck on his minstrel concert and he responded that it was "the best one that he ever had." She mentioned that the Charles Broadway Rouss Fund Club were having a meeting at her house. Tom wrote that after the minstrel show there was a parade and party at the Elks Lodge of Charlottesville until two o'clock in the morning. Ada also wrote about their friend, Paul Hall, and his love life and career.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 March 1-8, 15 items. (Box-folder 13:8)
    Tom wrote that the band was going to Atlantic City in July with the Elks; Louisville, Kentucky in May; and Washington D. C. with the Knights Templar; the University of Virginia for Easter; and Lynchburg. He also wrote that Professor Ide helped him with the music for the story of the reformation. Ada encouraged Tom to be the leader for the Stonewall Orchestra. Tom mentioned that a friend was getting an "absolute" divorce where one does not have to pay alimony.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 March 9-13, 10 items. (Box-folder 13:9)
    Tom sent in his application to the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind. Ada wrote him that she had almost made up her mind to marry him as soon as he made a "little headway" financially. Tom wrote that he was ecstatic and that they were both twenty-five with their best years being spent in loneliness. He said that he would give up his music for her so that he could get a better job, but she wrote him that she would not mind at all having to work.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 March 14-21, 9 items. (Box-folder 13:10)
    Tom wrote to Ada explaining that the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind did not pay as much as she seemed to think. With classes and the band Tom made thirty dollars per month including board and washing. Ada wanted to find someone to sell her art work for her. She also mentioned that Dick Byrd [Richard Evelyn Byrd] joined the Virginia Club.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 March 22-31, 12 items. (Box-folder 13:11)
    Tom wrote that he lost over a hundred dollars in stock and was very upset about it. He did not get the position at the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind because they reelected the person that resigned. Tom also mentioned that Mr. King was the secretary at the Mary Baldwin Seminary, and Mr. Webb was the principle music teacher at Miss Duvals. Ada wrote she would be interested in earning money as a personal companion.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 April 2-12, 19 items. (Box-folder 14:1)
    Ada asked Tom's advice on what to tell Paul Hall about their engagement and their desire to keep it secret. Tom wrote that he didn't understand why they couldn't get married and that he would come to get her as soon as she consented. He told her how much he missed her, even making sexual reference to his physical desire for her. He also wrote about his concern about the "B & Loan." [Baltimore Building and Loan Associates] He enclosed a program for his concert at the Mary Baldwin Seminary. Ada wrote about how the house was a little more peaceful since her Uncle Julius was away in Baltimore.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 April 13-23, 11 items. (Box-folder 14:2)
    Tom directed a concert at the University of Virginia and attended a University of Virginia baseball game against Yale. Tom tried to obtain advice from Doug Fuller regarding the stock of the Baltimore Building and Loan Associates. There is a printed letter to the shareholders explaining what had happened with the company. He also made explicit references regarding some of Ada's physical attributes and requested that Ada burn that part of his letter.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 April 24-30, 8 items. (Box-folder 14:3)
    Ada wrote to Tom reassuring him that his concert would be a success and that it would be good for him to stop by Buena Vista and see his mother who had not been well. She also advised Tom that he should tell his brother John to be sure and stretch as that would make him taller. Tom wrote that he attended the Virginia Female Institute recital and also the Mary Baldwin Seminary performance. There are programs for each of these events.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 May 1-14, 16 items. (Box-folder 14:4)
    Tom travelled to Lexington, Clifton Forge, Lynchburg, Buena Vista and Richmond, Virginia giving concerts and visiting his family. He wrote that he was busy writing music for marches such as Old Kentucky Home, Bonnie Blue Flag, and Maryland.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 May 15-31, 25 items. (Box-folder 14:5)
    Ada wrote about the Mason's parade and enclosed the program. She mentioned news about various friends and acquaintances including information about how someone was wearing a new style of underwear that absorbed all moisture. She told Tom that it cost eight dollars for "a set of these drawers." In addition to his music, Tom also sold pictures as a photographer.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 June 1-11, 14 items. (Box-folder 14:6)
    Ada received a letter from Paul Hall inviting her to Washington D. C. Tom wrote about his trip to Louisville Kentucky and after his concert, the town people gave him a key to the city. He also told her that he was performing with a [Charlottesville] Band on the Lawn of the University of Virginia the following week. Ada wrote about her intense desire to be independent and earn her own living.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 June 12-31, 21 items. (Box-folder 14:7)
    Ada feared that the summer would be the hardest yet for them to be apart. She complained that no one in the house cared for her and that she was more lonesome every day. Tom met Ada in Winchester for a dance which they both enjoyed. Ada promised that she would marry Tom that year. Tom met Mr. Paul Bowles from the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind and was given encouragement that they would have a place for him next year. Ada wrote that she saw Will Glass but did not really care one way or the other if he was cordial or not.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 July 1-18, 13 items. (Box-folder 15:1)
    Tom gave a concert in Clifton Forge, Virginia and had a great time bicycle riding, playing cards (whist) and picnicking with beer, whiskey, cigars, lemon ice, and cake. His band played songs like Home Sweet Home and Sunrise. Tom also gave several concerts in Atlantic City. Ada severely reprimanded Tom for playing whist on Sunday in Clifton Forge and for drinking in Atlantic City.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 July 19-31, 19 items. (Box-folder 15:2)
    Tom's mother visited Ada and her mother and the three of them became very good friends. Ada apologized for accusing him of drinking too much. Tom wrote about his photographs and his plans for setting up a dark room to develop his own pictures. Ada worried that Tom's father might move to Staunton and harm Tom's reputation. Ada wrote that William [Powell] visited her with his class pin and cap.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 August 1-11, 14 items. (Box-folder 15:3)
    Ada wrote that Thomas Jefferson Manning had been sick all summer. Tom wrote about buying a camera and supplies for developing his own pictures. Ada wanted Tom to come to Winchester for the summer and tried to entice him with descriptions of her in full "undress."
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 August 14-31, 16 items. (Box-folder 15:4)
    Tom wrote that he was waiting to hear more details about the position at the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind from Mr. Paul Bowles.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 September 1-13, 22 items. (Box-folder 15:5)
    Ada wrote to Tom at the White Sulphur Springs at the Greenbrier about how hateful her father was to her mother. She also mentioned that Mame Shriner was going to visit her mother. Tom wrote that he missed her and made explicit references about his desires for her. They also mentioned some photographs that Tom took of Ada which he burned because they were afraid someone might see them.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 September 14-30, 20 items. (Box-folder 15:6)
    Tom wrote that he received a position with the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind. Ada mentioned that her father was hateful and drunk. Ada asked Tom who he would vote for and he responded that he would support Bryan [William Jennings Bryan, Democratic candidate for the presidential election].
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 October 1-16, 16 items. (Box-folder 16:1)
    Ada wrote about Richard Beardsworth giving her father two weeks notice if he was going to leave the store and take another job. She also wrote that Paul Hall was sick with malaria. Tom wrote about furnishing his room and about teaching the blind students using point music.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 October 17-31, 18 items. (Box-folder 16:2)
    Tom wrote that keeping eight pianos in shape was very time consuming and he was very grateful for the work. He also mentioned that he was getting along very well with the blind boys and girls. He praised them saying that they were as good as any other mandolin and guitar clubs that he had.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 November 1-14, 19 items. (Box-folder 16:3)
    Ada and Tom wrote about the election of President William McKinley. Tom also wrote that the best claret could be found at the Monticello Claret for thirty five cents a quart. Tom wrote explicitly about his desire for Ada. He also wrote about how they both longed to have a little boy after they married and how eating too many sweets while pregnant could cause the baby to be a girl. There are also some braille music cards enclosed.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 November 15-30, 20 items. (Box-folder 16:4)
    Tom wrote to Ada that it would be nice to be married for awhile before having children but that they could not consider birth control unless it was safe. Ada wrote that Thomas Manning was very ill with typhoid fever. She also wrote that he would not recognize Winchester with all of its new storefronts and a new City Hall. Tom went to a school dance where girls were doing the "jig" and the "cakewalk." Tom wrote that he was still learning the point system and there is a braille music card included with his correspondence.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 December 1-14, 15 items. (Box-folder 16:5)
    Tom wrote that he didn't understand why Ada would not marry him yet, and she responded that they would marry when everything was right. The Board of the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind gave Tom a raise of fifty-four dollars per month. Ada was making dolls and selling them at the drugstore. Tom gave a performance at the Asylum for the Insane and at the Opera House. Tom wrote about wanting to see her when she was "washing" and inquired about her wanting him.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1900 December 15-30, 20 items. (Box-folder 16:6)
    Ada wrote to Tom encouraging him to help his brother John save his money to get a better education. Ada was concerned that Tom's mother was doing all of Lavinia's sewing and that it was affecting her health. Tom mentioned that a factory in Staunton burned causing many people to be out of work. Ada's mother fell during Christmas and sprained her ankle.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 January 1-14, 17 items. (Box-folder 17:1)
    Ada wrote that she was taking care of both of her parents, her mother for her ankle and her father's complaints. Tom's brother, Richard, stopped working for the Bantz's store and moved out of their house so that he could learn a new job. Ada wanted to obtain a good position in Washington D. C.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 January 15-31, 22 items. (Box-folder 17:2)
    Ada took care of her mother's ankle and her father had the grippe. Her cat named Mark Hanna [after the wealthy industrialist Mark Hanna] died. Tom taught classes for Professor Ide at the Mary Baldwin Seminary because the professor became ill. Tom lent his brother William "Willie" one hundred and fifty dollars so that he could go into business for himself.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 February 1-13, 14 items. (Box-folder 17:3)
    Tom mentioned Professor Minor at the Mary Baldwin Seminary. He also wrote that Professor Ide died of cancer. She encouraged Tom to ask Mr. Bowles about Professor Ide's position.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 February 14-28, 14 items. (Box-folder 17:4)
    Ada told Tom to deposit his money in the bank and not give it to his brother, Willie. Tom reassured her that his family was not imposing on him. He was giving ninety lessons per week and attending band practice twice a week. He sent Ada a program for his students' recital with their names underlined by him.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 March 1-16, 15 items. (Box-folder 17:5)
    Ada travelled to Washington D. C. for her birthday, to see the presidential inauguration of William McKinley and to visit with the Halls and Mr. Rouss. Ada wrote that she went out to dinner with a famous photographer of the time, Barnett Mcfee Clinedinst. She was also still trying to find a job at the Post Office. Tom wrote about his strong physical desires for her.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 March 17-31, 14 items. (Box-folder 17:6)
    Tom mentioned playing benefit concerts for the Y.M.C.A. He also described his friend, Mr. Minor as a young lawyer, a member of his Bible class and the son of a teacher at the Virginia Female Institute. Ada wrote about her typewriting class and an exam for the Post Office.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 April 1-13, 13 items. (Box-folder 17:7)
    Ada explained to him that she wanted to be able to earn money for herself so that she could buy things and that her father was delighted that she was trying to get a position. Ada wrote that she would still love Tom if he did not get his position for next winter. Included in the correspondence are programs for Carpenter's Quo Vadis at the Staunton Opera House and Mr. Carr's recital of Popular Classical Songs.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 April 15-29, 16 items. (Box-folder 17:8)
    Ada wrote to Tom about how strongly she wanted to obtain a position but did not want to write her reasons on paper She received a letter from General Thomas L. Rosser who was helping her to obtain a position with the Post Office in Washington D. C. for seventy five dollars per month. She mentioned wanting to see the performances of Joseph Jefferson and the Maurice [Glian] Opera Company in New York and not having enough money to attend. She also enclosed a lock of her hair from when she was five years old. On a personal note she wrote to Tom, "Your pretties are all the same and waiting for you to love them a lot. Heaven knows they want it bad enough." Tom wrote that he voted for the [1902 Constitutional Convention of Virginia] represented by [Julian Minor] Quarles and [Allen Caperton] Braxton which imposed barriers for African Americans to vote. There is also a music program for the West Augusta Guards.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 May 3-24, 12 items. (Box-folder 17:9)
    Ada went to visit the Hall family in Brooklyn, New York and was so busy going to plays and seeing friends that she did not write Tom very much. Tom pled with Ada to write more and threatened to go to New York to make sure everything was alright. Ada decided to stay in New York and take shorthand classes. Tom wrote that he had an Alumni meeting at Mary Baldwin Seminary.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 June-July, 11 items. (Box-folder 18:1)
    Tom received a promotion at the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind and went to New York to visit Ada. He also had lunch with Walter Damrosch. Tom felt that he was taking second place to Ada since she stayed in New York.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 August-September 10, 23 items. (Box-folder 18:2)
    Tom went to Buffalo, New York with the Stonewall Brigade Band for the [Pan American Exposition in August where President William McKinley was later assassinated on September 6 but the letters do not mention this incident]. Ada returned to Winchester and wrote about Blanche and Richard Ross visiting her. Tom wrote about the [Entre Nous] Club which was composed of the nicest young people in town. He also wished that he and Ada could be together "for always."
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 September 11-30, 21 items. (Box-folder 18:3)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 October, 21 items. (Box-folder 18:4)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 November 2-29, 23 items. (Box-folder 18:5)
    Ada wrote that she did not care for Paul Hall and that she wanted to marry Tom but could not yet come to Staunton to be with him because his position as a teacher would not allow his reputation to be questioned. Ada went back to New York to take classes. Ada wrote that he must not make himself ill for not having her.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1901 December, 15 items. (Box-folder 18:6)
    Ada wrote that she would give Tom an answer before the end of the next summer. She also mentioned that the windows of Macy's store were a moving panorama.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 January 1-21, 15 items. (Box-folder 18:7)
    Ada wrote to Tom about his father's death. She also wrote about her visits with her friend, George Schoenfelt but did not tell Tom that George was in love with her. George collected money for an insurance company and took her with him on his drives to collect the money. Ada wrote that she would marry Tom later in the year. Tom wrote that he was sorry that she would have to work after they were married but she responded that she wanted to work. He was delighted that he could tell his mother about their plans to marry.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 January 22-31, 10 items. (Box-folder 18:7)
    Tom mentioned the St. Louis Exposition.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 January 22-31, 10 items. (Box-folder 18:8)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth, 1902 February 1-14, 21 items. (Box-folder 18:9)
    Tom bought a house for him and Ada in Staunton for twenty five hundred dollars. Tom wanted to write to Ada's father about marrying her. Ada wrote that her family didn't have any money to give him when they would marry. She did not want Tom to write to her father until she went to Baltimore because she expected that he "will raise the roof." She also wrote that he was taking a burden by getting married and that he did not realize all of the expenses that it would incur.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 February 15-28 (Box-folder 18:10)
    Ada wrote that Water Street and Main Street in Winchester were still flooded. She also mentioned a public hanging. Tom wrote that the mandolin club played at the Asylum for the Insane. Tom also wrote that the Institute for the Deaf and Blind would vote on the teachers for the next two years.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 March 1-14, 14 items. (Box-folder 19:1)
    Tom wrote that he heard the Honorable H. St. George Tucker address the Dunsmore Business College while his band played for them. The Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind offered Tom his same position with an increase of one hundred dollars per month. Ada wrote about her neuralgia and her eyes and mentioned that she would have Dr. Hunter McGuire look at them. She also wrote that Charles Broadway Rouss died.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 March 15-30, 16 items. (Box-folder 19:2)